這就是我們的搖籃
Yes, this is home.
這就是地球
This is Earth.
找不到熟悉的大陸嗎
Having trouble finding a familiar continent?
這是因為過去的地球與現在完全不同
The past is another planet. Actually, many.
而在我腳下的 就是宇宙大爆炸以來的所有時間
I'm standing on the great expanse of time that has elapsed since the Big Bang.
為了更好地理解大爆炸後發生了什麼
In order to think about it,
我們把時間壓縮成1年
we've compressed it all into a single year.
現在是宇宙年歷上的12月23號的清晨
It's the early morning of December 23 on this Cosmic Calendar of ours,
大約3億5千萬年前
or about 350 million years ago,
當時我們的世界才剛剛40億歲
when our world was a mere four billion years old.
地球看上去完全不同
Earth looks so different.
你完全認不出來
You might not even know the place.
天上的星星也幫不了你
The stars wouldn't help you.
當時的星座也和現在的不一樣
Even the constellations would have been different back then.
恐龍要在1億多年後才會出現
The dinosaurs were still more than 100 million years in the future.
那時候也沒有鳥 沒有花
There were no birds, no flowers.
就連空氣都不一樣
And the air was different, too.
大氣層中的氧氣濃度空前絕後地高
The atmosphere had more oxygen than at any other time in Earth's history,  before or since.
這使得昆蟲可以長得比現在大得多
This allowed insects to grow much larger than they do today.
怎麼會這樣
How?
昆蟲沒有肺
Insects don't have lungs.
它們由身體上對外的開口獲得生命必須的氧氣
Life-giving oxygen is taken in through openings in the outside of their bodies
然後通過管道網絡傳遍全身
and transported through a network of tubes.
如果昆蟲長得太大
If an insect were too large,
這些管道的外圍就會吸收盡所有的氧氣
the outer reaches of these tubes would absorb all the oxygen
氧氣就無法到達內部的器官
before it could ever get to its internal organs.
但是在石炭紀
But during the Carboniferous Period,
距今2.9-3.55億年
大氣層的氧氣濃度是現在的兩倍
the atmosphere had almost twice the oxygen as today.
昆蟲可以長得很大
Insects could then grow much bigger
依然可以獲得足夠的氧氣
and still get enough oxygen in their bodies.
這就是為什麼 蜻蜓可以和老鷹一樣大
That's why the dragonflies here are as big as eagles
千足蟲和鱷魚一樣大
and the millipedes the size of alligators.
那麼為什麼那時候會有如此充足的氧氣呢
So why was there so much oxygen back then?
其實它們都由一個全新的生物製造的
It was produced by a new kind of life.
中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain timhal
Bluray版字幕製作  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第九集
是什麼樣的生物讓大氣層發生了這麼戲劇化的變化
What kind of life could've changed the Earth's atmosphere so dramatically?
這些參天的植物
Plants that could reach for the sky
大樹
trees.
在它們為了獲得陽光的競賽中 進化出了抵抗引力的方式
In their competition for sunlight, trees evolved a way to defy gravity.
樹出現以前 最高的植物
Before trees, the tallest vegetation was
只不過高及腰際
only about waist-high.
然後奇跡發生了
And then something wonderful happened.
一個植物分子在強度和彈性方面都獲得了進化
A plant molecule evolved that was both strong and flexible,
這種材料可以支撐很大的重量
a material that could support a lot of weight,
也可以在風中彎曲而不折斷
yet bend in the wind without breaking.
木質素造就了樹的誕生
Lignin made trees possible.
現在生命可以向上發展
Now life could build upward.
並且打開了一片全新的領域
And this opened a whole new territory,
這些遠離地面的群體形成一個三維的世界
a three-dimensional matrix for communities far above the ground.
地球變成了樹的世界
Earth became the Planet of the Trees.
但是木質素有個缺點
But lignin had a downside
不易食
it was hard to swallow.
天然拆遷辦成員 真菌和細菌
When nature's demolition crew, the fungi and bacteria,
負責消化一切有木質素的物體
tried to eat anything with lignin in it,
結果就是嚴重的消化不良
they got a really bad case of indigestion.
白蟻要在至少1億年後才會進化出來
And termites wouldn't evolve for at least another 100 million years.
該拿那些死掉的樹怎麼辦呢
What to do with all those dead trees?
真菌和細菌花費了幾百萬年
It took the fungi and bacteria millions of years
才進化出消化它們的化學方法
to evolve the biochemical means to consume them.
與此同時 樹不斷地生長
Meanwhile, the trees just kept springing up,
死亡 倒下
dying, falling over
再由萬年積累的泥土覆蓋
and getting buried by the mud that built up over eons.
最終 億萬的樹
Eventually, there were hundreds of billions of trees
被深埋地下
entombed in the Earth,
被埋葬在世界各地的森林
buried forests all over the Earth.
那會帶來什麼潛在的危害呢
What possible harm could come from that?
新斯科捨省的這個懸崖是另一種年歷
This cliff in Nova Scotia is another kind of calendar.
它訴說著另一個曾經在這裏繁榮世界的故事
It tells the story of that other world that once flourished right here.
這是一棵3億年古樹的死亡面具
And this is the death mask of that 300 million-year-old tree.
它由礦物打造 礦物替代了原本的木頭
It was cast by minerals that replaced the original wood
替代了每一個細胞 它又被稱為 化石
cell by cell-- in other words, a fossil.
很久以前 樹將它的有機分子擴散到周圍的環境中
The tree surrendered its organic molecules to the environment long ago,
包括碳元素和水分 只留下它的形狀
its carbon and water. Only its shape remains.
這棵樹還活著時 它吸入二氧化碳
When this tree was alive, it took in carbon dioxide
還有水分 利用陽光
and water and used sunlight
把它們轉化成富含能量的有機物
to turn them into energy-rich organic matter.
然後把氧氣作為廢物排出
The tree gave off oxygen as a waste product.
至今樹和其他植物依然是這樣做的
That's what trees and other plants still do.
植物死亡後 它們腐爛
When plants die, they decay,
並且反轉那個過程
and this reverses the transaction.
它們的有機物與氧氣結合
Their organic matter combines with oxygen
然後分解
and decomposes,
將二氧化碳排放到空氣中
putting carbon dioxide back into the air.
這使得地球大氣層的化學物質達到平衡
This balances the books for the chemistry of Earth's atmosphere.
如果樹在腐爛前就被埋葬
But if the trees are buried before they can decay,
那會發生兩件事 它們帶著碳元素
two things happen... they take the carbon
並將太陽能儲藏在裏面
and stored solar energy with them
不帶走氧氣
and leave the oxygen behind
任由它在大氣中積累
to build up in the atmosphere.
這就是3億年前的狀況
That's what happened around 300 million years ago.
當時氧氣過剩
There was an oxygen surplus.
因此蟲子們可以長得如此巨大
That's how the bugs got so big.
那些被掩埋的碳又會怎樣呢
And what became of all that buried carbon?
它們與世隔絕 深埋地下億萬年
It lay there for eons before dealing life on Earth
然後發生了有史以來最具毀滅性的爆發
its most devastating blow of all time.
在地球上有些地方 你可以跨越時間
There are places on this planet where you can walk through time
閱讀岩石中蘊含的歷史
and read the history written in the rocks.
新斯科捨省的海灘就是這樣的一個地方
This beach in Nova Scotia is one of them.
每一層都是一頁書
Every layer is a page.
每一層都訴說著一個大洪水的故事
Each one tells the story of a flood,
一個接一個 持續幾百萬年
one after another, over millions of years.
像夾心蛋糕一樣的洪水沉積層 逐漸被掩埋
The layer cake of flood deposits was slowly buried
在溫度和壓力的作用下 變為岩石
and turned into rock by heat and pressure.
這些同樣的力量產生了山脈
The same forces that built mountains
連同被埋葬的化石森林一起
then tilted and uplifted them,
在它們的基礎上 傾斜再慢慢積高
along with the entombed fossil forest.
新的岩層總是堆積在老的岩層之上
The newer layers were always deposited on top of the older ones.
就如所有的書頁都按照正確的順序排列
All the pages are in the correct order,
記錄著幾百萬年來這裏曾經的故事
bearing witness to what happened here over millions of years.
後面那裏 藏著更古老的過去
Back that way lies the more distant past.
我每向前走一步
And with every step I take,
相當於向現在邁進1千年
I move about 1,000 years closer to the present
同時遠離那個3億年前的世界
and away from the world of 300 million years ago.
那邊就是5千萬年後
50 million years later lies that way.
這是二疊紀末期的開始
This was the beginning of the end of the Permian world,
也就是一場無與倫比的大滅絕
an event of unequalled carnage.
二疊紀是滅絕紀念堂裏
The Permian is the darkest corridor
最沉重的一條走廊 也是紀念生命之樹上
in this memorial to the broken branches on the Tree of Life--
其中的一根斷枝
the Halls of Extinction.
2億5千萬年來
Death has never come so close
死神從沒像這樣般 想要統治整個世界
to reigning supreme on this world in the quarter billion years since.
在現今西伯利亞發生的火山爆發
The eruptions, in what is now Siberia,
持續了幾十萬年
lasted for hundreds of thousands of years.
熔漿燒燬了上百萬平方英里的地方
The lava flooded and buried more than a million square miles.
這次的災難使其他歷史時期的火山爆發相形見絀
This event dwarfs any volcanic eruption in historical times.
滅絕紀念堂
從火山裂縫中洩出大量的二氧化碳
Huge quantities of carbon dioxide came pouring out of the volcanic fissures
這溫室氣體使得大氣溫度不斷攀升
This greenhouse gas warmed the climate.
使得早先在石炭紀就被埋葬的森林再次回到我們的故事中
And this is where the long-buried forests of the earlier Carboniferous Period reenter the story.
在5千萬年的時間裏
During the intervening 50 million years,
那些樹變成了巨大的煤礦
those trees had turned into immense deposits of coal,
就因為這樣
and as it happened,
世界上最大儲量的煤礦之一
one of the world's largest accumulations of coal
就被埋在西伯利亞
was buried right there in Siberia.
熔岩的溫度烘烤著煤
The heat from the lava baked the coal,
促使沼氣和富硫氣體衝出地表
driving methane and sulfur-rich gases out of the ground.
同時滿載著有毒的放射性塵埃微粒
They were laden with toxic and radioactive ash particles
這就是煤煙
coal smoke.
這種邪惡的混合物對空氣造成了嚴重的污染
This witch's brew polluted the atmosphere
也從根本上導致了地球溫度的失衡
and radically destabilized Earth's climate.
硫酸霧霾隔絕了陽光 使地球陷入黑暗
A sulfuric acid haze blocked incoming sunlight and darkened the planet
全球溫度驟降至冰點以下
Global temperatures plummeted to subfreezing.
在火山噴發的間歇期
During lulls in the eruptions,
硫酸霧霾落回地面
the acid haze fell back to the surface.
但是二氧化碳繼續
But the carbon dioxide remained
在空氣中累積 導致全球變暖
and built up in the atmosphere to cause global warming.
多年的嚴寒與上千年的酷熱交替出現
Years of frigid cold alternating with millennia of stifling heat
導致了動植物的數量減少
battered a dwindling population of plants and animals.
它們沒有機會去適應劇烈的氣溫變化
They had no chance to adapt to the drastic swings in climate.
隨著全球變暖的持續
As the global warmingcontinued,
表層和深層的水逐漸混合
the surface and the bottom waters slowly mixed,
使曾經冰冷的海床水溫升高
raising the temperature of the once-frigid depths of the sea floor.
令沉積物中富含沼氣的冰也開始融化
Methane-rich ices that had been frozen in the sediments began to melt.
重獲自由的沼氣浮上水面並且進入空氣中
Newly liberated methane gas made its way to the surface and into the atmosphere.
而沼氣比二氧化碳能夠更有效地吸收熱量
Methane traps heat far more efficiently than carbon dioxide
於是氣候變得更炎熱
so the climate got even hotter.
沼氣也破壞了了平流層中的臭氧層
And the methane also destroyed the ozone layer in the stratosphere
保護生物不受致命紫外線傷害的天然防曬霜 已經被侵蝕了
The natural sunscreen that protects life from deadly ultraviolet rays was eaten away.
全球海洋的循環系統停止了工作
The circulatory system of the world ocean shut down.
水裏的空氣耗盡
These stagnant waters became oxygen-starved,
殺死了大海中幾乎所有的魚類
killing almost all the fish in the sea.
但有一種生物在這殘酷的環境中得以繁榮
But one kind of life flourished in this brutal environment...
那是能排泄出硫化氫的一種細菌
bacteria that produced deadly hydrogen sulfide gas as a waste product.
它也是壓死駱駝的最後一根稻草
That was the last straw.
有毒氣體殺死了陸地上幾乎其他所有的植物和動物
The poison gas killed almost all the remaining plants and animals on the land.
這就是大滅絕
This was the Great Dying.
地球上生命最接近全部滅絕的一次
The closest life on Earth has ever come to annihilation.
十分之九的物種不復存在
Nine in ten of all species perished.
地球花費了很久才使生命重燃生機
It took a long time for life to bounce back.
而這幾百萬年 地球可以用
For a few million years, Earth could have been called
"死氣沉沉"來形容
the Planet of the Dead.
我們的祖先是少數倖存物種之一
We are descended from one of the few species that managed to squeak by
你作為人類 並且現在還能存在
You are human and alive at this very moment
都應該歸功於它們將DNA
because they managed to endure, conveying
從這生物歷史上最危險的時期
their DNA through one of the most treacherous periods
延續下來
in the history of life.
這座山脈完全由生物組成
This mountain was made entirely by life.
在地獄大門大開之前
The life that flourished back in the glory days
這些生物都曾經在二疊紀有著輝煌的過去
of the Permian, before all hell broke loose.
這裏是長達400英里的瓜達魯普山脈的一部分
This is part of the 400 mile-long
貫穿德克薩斯和新墨西哥州
Guadalupe Mountain chain that runs through Texas and New Mexico
世界上最大的化石巖礁
It's the world's largest fossil reef.
這裏曾是一大片內陸海
All this was once a great inland sea.
這個巖礁欣欣向榮了好幾百年
The reef flourished and grew for millions of years,
她曾是海綿生物 綠藻生物
and was home to multitudes of sponges, green algae,
還有很多小得看不見的生物賴以為生的家
and animals too small to see.
這些生物死亡後
When these creatures died,
它們沉到海底 並被淤泥覆蓋
they sank to the bottom and were buried in the silt.
幾百萬年後
Over millions of years,
它們的殘骸變成石油和天然氣
their remains were converted into oil and gas.
最終 盆地被淤泥填滿 巖礁死亡
Eventually, the basin silted in and the reef died.
然後 這座海底鬼城被深埋在地下一英里處
This marine ghost town was then buried a mile beneath the surface.
後來 構造作用力將骷髏般的巖礁推上海平面
Later, tectonic forces lifted the skeletal reef high above sea level,
於是它又被風雨侵蝕了無數年
where it was eroded and sculpted over eons by wind and rain.
想像一下這裏2.75億年前的樣子
Just imagine what this place looked like 275 million years ago,
那時候的熱帶內陸海有幾座小島在海中漂浮著 海水裏充滿了生氣
when it was a vibrant, tropical inland sea, dotted with islands
生命之火還在那熊熊燃燒著
and brimming with life.
而在大約2.2億年前
Until about 220 million years ago,
新英格蘭和北美洲還靠得很近
New England and North Africa were next-door neighbors.
那時還沒有大西洋
There was no such thing as the Atlantic Ocean.
中間那些藍色的狹長地帶 還只是湖
Those thin blue fingers at the center-- they were lakes.
它們是超大陸分裂的最初顯著標誌
They were the first outward signs that the supercontinent
同時也預示了地球上的生命將迎來又一次的巨變
was splitting apart and that life on Earth was due for another big shake-up.
1百萬年後 這些湖變成了一條長長的海灣
A million years later, the lakes became a long bay,
然後逐漸變成大西洋
which would grow into the Atlantic Ocean.
地表的這些意義重大的變化
These profound changes at the surface
卻遠遠無法與地球深處發生的變化相提並論
were merely symptoms of a drama that was unfolding far beneath, in the depths of the Earth.
人類出現時 這些可以揭示地球劇變的
By the time we got here, the telltale traces
蛛絲馬跡已被淹沒在大洋深處
of global upheaval were buried at the bottom of the deep blue sea.
我們已經完全不清楚地球殘酷無比的過去
We were completely cut off from the great story of Earth's violent past
就像失憶癥患者一樣迫切的想要知道
a species of amnesiacs trying to find out
他們是誰 以前究竟發生了什麼
who we were and what happened before we awakened.
1570年亞伯拉罕·奧特柳斯繪製了首張
In 1570, Abraham Ortelius created the first
現代世界地圖 都歸功於
modern world atlas, reflecting on the discoveries
過去80年熱衷探索的黃金時代裏的偉大發現
of the previous 80 years-- the Golden Age of Exploration.
還沒等墨跡乾透
Before the ink was dry,
奧特柳斯便已經開始仔細審視他的傑作
Ortelius stepped back from his masterpiece
他首先發現了
and became the first of many to notice the striking
大西洋兩側的大陸邊緣相互吻合
puzzle-piece fit between the continent on either side of the Atlantic.
他隨後寫道 美洲是因為地震和洪水
He later wrote that the Americas were torn away
才與歐非大陸分離開
from Europe and Africa by earthquakes and floods.
但是奧特柳斯的觀察結論
But Ortelius's observation
在隨後的幾百年裏 都被認為那只不過是他的直覺而已
remained nothing more than a hunch for the next couple of centuries...
直到20世紀早期
until an early 20th century
德國的一位天文學家兼氣象學家
German astronomer and meteorologist
才用積累的證據 使之成為一個科學理論
amassed the evidence to build the scientific case for it.
第一次世界大戰期間 阿爾弗雷德·魏格納應徵入伍
Alfred Wegener had been drafted during the First World War,
不久就負傷
but was wounded soon after.
在戰地醫院恢復期間
As he recovered in a field hospital,
他從科學文獻中搜尋地球往事的線索
he scoured scientific literature for clues to the Earth's past.
多年前
Years before,
魏格納在大學圖書館裏偶爾讀了一篇有趣的論文
Wegener had happened upon an intriguing paper in the stacks of his university library.
魏格納迷惑了
It puzzled Wegener
現在已經滅絕的同種蕨類化石
that fossils of the same species of a now-extinct fern
竟然在大西洋兩岸都有發現它們的報道
were reported to be found on both sides of the Atlantic.
更令人驚奇的是 同種類的恐龍化石
Even more curious were the discoveries of fossils
也在兩邊的大陸都有發現
of the same dinosaurs on both continents.
而在20世紀早期
In the early 20th century,
地質學家對這種現象做了解釋
geologists explained how life crossed the oceans
他們想像兩塊大陸間曾經有一塊陸地連接
by imagining that land bridges had once existed between them.
他們相信這些連接的陸地在之前逐漸瓦解
It was thought that these land bridges gradually disintegrated
然後消失在海底了
and vanished beneath the waves long ago.
但是有一個證據使得魏格納相信
But there was one piece of evidence that convinced Wegener
這個主流的科學觀點肯定錯了
that the prevailing scientific view must be wrong...
證據就是地球本身
the Earth itself.
一條山脈怎麼會跨越海洋的分割
Why would a mountain range cross the oceanic divide
又在另一塊大陸繼續綿延
to continue on another continent?
為什麼巴西和南非所發現的岩石
And why would you find the same unique pattern
有著相同的獨特構造規律
in the layers of rocks in both Brazil and South Africa?
還有
And another thing...
為什麼熱帶的植物
under what circumstances could tropical plants have flourished
居然會出現在北冰洋的冰天雪地中
in the frozen wastes of the Arctic?
魏格納推斷只有一種符合邏輯的解釋
Wegener concluded that there was only one logical solution to this puzzle...
地球上曾經有一塊超級大陸
There had once been a single supercontinent on Earth.
他稱之為 盤古大陸
He named it Pangaea.
魏格納因此成為科學界的寵兒了嗎
So Wegener becomes the toast of the scientific world, right?
並沒有
Not exactly.
大多數的地質學家嘲笑他的大陸漂移猜想
Most geologists ridiculed Wegener's hypothesis of continental drift.
他們更傾向於用他們的天然陸地連接理論
They preferred their imaginary natural land bridges
對魏格納提出的證據作出解釋
to explain away Wegener's evidence.
他們質疑大陸怎麼可能會破開海床堅硬的岩石呢
How, they asked, could a continent plow through the solid rock of the ocean floor?
魏格納並沒有令人信服的答案
Wegener had no convincing answer.
他成了這個領域的笑柄
He became the laughingstock of the field;
學術會議中的棄兒
a pariah at scientific conferences.
儘管如此 魏格納依然堅持他的理論
Despite this, Wegener continued to fight for his ideas,
為了收集證據進行大膽的科學研究考察
conducting daring research expeditions to gather evidence.
其中又一次 他得知同事們
On one of these, he learned that colleagues were
被困在冰冠中 沒有食物
trapped on an ice cap without food.
在他增援後的返回途中
On his way back from the mission,
他迷失在了暴風雪中
he became lost in a blizzard.
就在他50歲生日過後的一兩天
A day or two after his 50th birthday,
他失蹤了
he disappeared,
他永遠不知道 他的觀點被證明是正確的 而他被視為
he would be vindicated and come to be viewed
歷史上最偉大的地質學家之一
as one of the greatest geologists in history.
科學家也是人
Scientists are human.
也有盲點和偏見
We have our blind spots and prejudices.
科學是一種機制 就是要掃除這些盲點和偏見
Science is a mechanism designed to ferret them out
問題是 我們並非一直忠誠於這個科學的核心價值
Problem is, we aren't always faithful to the core values of science
瑪麗·薩普就深知其中的精髓
Few people knew this better than Marie Tharp.
1952年 瑪麗耐心地忍受著地質系同事的輕視
It's 1952, and Marie is patiently enduring the slights of her fellow members of the geology department.
她的地質學學位和數學專業並不被他們放在眼裏
Her degrees in geology and mathematics count for little with them.
布魯斯·希森 一位愛荷華州來的研究生
Bruce Heezen, a graduate student from Iowa,
剛剛結束了漫長的科考探險
has just returned from a lengthy expedition
他們用聲納繪製海床圖
to map the ocean floor using sonar.
你能看看這些能用來做什麼吧
Will you do something with these?
布魯斯 你瞧
Bruce, look.
一切都很明瞭
It's-- it's all come together.
這條大裂谷
There's this giant rift valley
貫穿整個大西洋底部
that runs through the bottom of the Atlantic.
得了吧 瑪麗
Aw, geez, Marie, come on.
又是這些廢話
This is just more girl talk.
你還沒受夠它們帶給你的麻煩嗎
You're not in enough trouble with everyone here already?
這簡直就是大陸漂移理論
This sounds too much like continental drift.
你想淪落到魏格納那樣嗎
You want to end up like Wegener?
但是瑪麗不為所動
But Marie would not be dissuaded.
多年後 瑪麗和布魯斯將一張海洋震央圖
Years later, when Marie and Bruce placed a map of oceanic
放上看片台 蓋在她的海底地圖上時
earthquake epicenters on a light table over her seafloor map,
地震點遍佈整個大裂谷
the earthquakes fell right along the rift valley.
這就是魏格納漂移理論的確鑿證據
This was the smoking gun for Wegener's moving continents.
海底山脊的最高點
希森終於知道
Heezen now knew
原來瑪麗一直都是對的
that Marie had been right all along.
他們共同繪製了第一張真正意義上的地球地圖
Together, they created the first true map of the Earth,
包括了海底
including the ocean floor.
這使得我們終於可以開始解讀地球的自傳
We were at last ready to read the autobiography of the Earth.
讓我們乘坐想像之舟
Let's take the Ship of the Imagination...
進入對大部分人來說的都是深不可及的地方
to a part of the world that has been off-limits to all but a few of us
地球的三分之二
Two-thirds of the Earth
都處在1千英尺的水下
lies beneath more than 1,000 feet of water.
約300米左右
如此的廣闊 大部分都未經勘探
It's a vast and largely unexplored frontier.
所有人都知道阿爾卑斯山脈和落基山脈
Everybody knows the Alps and the Rockies,
但一些世界上最壯觀的山脈都被隱藏起來了
but some of the world's most amazing mountain ranges are hidden from view.
當我們到達水面下1千米這個日光照射不到的世界
Below 1,000 meters, we enter a world where there is no sunlight.
一個隱藏在黑暗中的神奇世界
Hidden in the darkness, a world of wonders.
這是世界上最長的海底山脈
This is the longest submarine mountain range in the world,
大西洋洋中脊
the Atlantic Mid-Ocean Ridge.
其橫跨大西洋及北冰洋 每年都以5至10厘米的速度向東西方向成長
它在我們的星球上形成一條宛如籃球接縫的線
It wraps around our globe like the seam on a baseball.
在過去 我們的星球與現在截然不同
The past is another planet,
但是大多數人也不瞭解現在這個星球
but most of us don't really know this one.
由於被水覆蓋 我們看不見這些山脈
We don't see the mountains for the water.
這就是瑪麗·薩普最初想像的世界
This is the world that Marie Tharp was the first to imagine.
山脊的最高峰
The highest peaks of the ridge
超出海底4千米
rise over four kilometers above the ocean floor
還有很多延綿的山脈和峽谷
There are sprawling mountain ranges and canyons, too.
我們現在進入馬裏亞納海溝
We've now entered the Marianas Trench,
海溝地處北太平洋西方海床
海溝底部於海平面下之深度 遠勝珠穆朗瑪峰海平面上之高度
地球上最深的峽谷
the deepest canyon on Earth,
超過1萬米的深度
more than ten kilometers deep.
它形成構造力將海床推擠到
It formed when tectonic forces pushed the seabed
相鄰的大陸板塊下
under the adjoining continental plate.
上過月球的人
More people have walked on the Moon
比下來這裏的多
than have ever been down here.
這裏的壓力達到了每平方英吋8噸
The pressure here is a crushing eight tons per square inch.
這樣的深度
Being this deep in the ocean
就像是50架波音747疊在一起
is like having 50 jumbo jets stacked on top of you.
即使在這裏 也有生命的存在
Yet even here, life has taken hold.
儘管陽光無法穿過這麼深的海水
The fact that sunlight can't penetrate the deep ocean
但並不意味著這裏沒有光
doesn't mean there isn't light down here.
許多水下生物在暗中發光
Many underwater species glow in the dark,
我們稱之為生物螢光
through a process called bioluminescence.
我們作為陸地上的哺乳動物
Our long history as land mammals,
有著生活在陽光普照下的悠久歷史
denizens of the sunlit world, hasn't prepared us
使我們沒有像海底深處多種多樣的生物那樣的進化
for the amazing variety of life that evolution has crafted in the deep oceans.
因為這裏沒有陽光
Since there's no sunlight down here,
也就沒有光合作用
there's no photosynthesis.
意味著沒有植物可供食用
That means there are no plants to feed on,
可即使在這樣一個沒有陽光的世界
and yet, even here, in a world of permanent midnight,
也有一條繁榮的食物鏈
there's a thriving food chain.
它由化學合成開始
It begins with a process called chemosynthesis
這些只有顯微鏡下可見的生物
These microscopic creatures have learned to eat
學會了食用那個孔裏出來的東西
what's pouring out of that vent...
一種被稱為硫化氫的有毒混合物
a noxious compound called hydrogen sulfide.
那濃密的黑煙提供了化學能量
That thick black smoke provides the chemical energy
使得生命得以在此生存
that makes life possible here.
小甲殼動物吃細菌
Tiny crustaceans eat the bacteria,
大一些的動物吃小甲殼動物
and the larger animals eat the crustaceans.
地球未來的某一天
One day, on some future Earth,
這些山脈很有可能露出水面
these mountains could very well end up above the water.
構造作用力持續改變著地球的外貌
Tectonic forces continue to shape our planet.
未來也會和現在截然不同
The future is also another planet.
以前 一個像這樣的火山
It was a volcano like this one
在數百萬年前 創造了夏威夷群島
that created the Hawaiian islands millions of years ago.
我們住在一個沸騰大鍋的外殼上
We live on the crust of a seething cauldron.
地球的中心有一個大鐵芯
At the center of our planet, there's an iron core.
它被包裹在一個液體的鐵殼內
It's nested inside of a larger, liquid iron shell.
再外層的部分稱之為地幔
Wrapped over this is the part called the mantle.
它是岩石構成 卻很熱很黏
It's rocky but hot and viscous.
就像是爐子上的一鍋濃湯
Like a pot of soup cooking on a stove,
不斷地翻騰
the mantle is churning.
是什麼使它翻騰呢
What keeps it moving?
兩樣東西 一個是地球形成時遺留的高溫
Two things... the heat left over from Earth's formation,
另一個就是地核中放射性物質的衰變
and the decay of radioactive elements in the core.
而這個外層 地殼
And this outer layer-- the crust,
你 我 大家所生活的地方
where you and me and everyone we know lives--
厚度卻只相當於蘋果皮
is only as thick as the skin on an apple.
地幔拖動固體的覆蓋層一起移動
The mantle drags the solid overlying crust along with it.
冷峻堅硬的地殼並不隨其所願
The crust resists because it's cool and rigid.
久而久之 到達了臨界點
From time to time, it reaches the breaking point.
到了那時 大地開始搖晃
When that happens, the Earth quakes.
並不是有人不聽話要受到懲罰
It's not because somebody misbehaved and is being punished.
它只是自然法則控制下的隨機力
It's due to random forces that are governed by the laws of nature.
因為我們生存的時間太短NOur sense of the stability of the Earth is an illusion
造成了我們對於地球穩定感的幻覺\
due to the shortness of our lives.
如果我們可以用地球本身的時間刻度觀察
If we could watch our planet on its own timescale,
重大的變化要用上百萬年的時間才可以顯現出來
in which big changes take millions of years to play out,
那時我們才可以看出它是怎樣的一個動態有機體
we would see it as the dynamic organism it really is.
這是三疊紀晚期時的世界
This is the world of the late Triassic period
距離現今約2億年
about 200 million years ago.
那個小傢伙
That little guy?
是我們的遠古祖先之一
It's one of our distant ancestors.
它所在地方就是現在的新澤西州的紐瓦克
He lived in Newark, New Jersey.
不論你在地球上的什麼地方
Wherever you walk on Earth...
你的腳下都曾經有一個失落的世界
lost worlds lie buried beneath your feet.
5千萬到1億年前
50 or 100 million years ago,
大部分貌似平常的地方
even the most seemingly ordinary places
都經歷了史詩般的變化
have been the scene of epic change.
這些巖壁就是盤古大陸分裂的紀念碑
These Palisades are a monument to the breakup of the supercontinent Pangaea.
連續的火山噴發
The sequence of volcanic eruptions
使這些懸崖導致了另一場大滅絕
that made these cliffs also led to the next mass extinction--
這場大滅絕宣告了三疊紀的終結
the one that ended the Triassic world.
但是造成一個物種滅絕的大災難
But a catastrophic extinction event for one species
卻是另一個物種的寶貴機遇
is a golden opportunity for another.
三疊紀的物種滅絕給了
The Triassic extinctions offered one group
另一個物種登上世界舞台中心的機會
that had been around for a while the chance to take center stage.
恐龍們愉快茁壯地生活了大約1.7億年
The dinosaurs had a good, long run for 170 million years.
那時 印度還是一個島
Back then, India was an island.
每年向北方慢慢爬行幾英吋
It crept northward at the pace of a few inches per year
雖然緩慢的 但也無法阻擋它向亞洲靠攏
on its slow but inexorable rendezvous with Asia.
然後 再一次
Then, once again,
地表下的熔岩
the molten rock beneath Earth's surface
噴射而出並且淹沒了印度西部的大部分
burst forth and flooded a huge area of western India.
致命的一擊從天而降
The knockout punch literally came out of the blue.
一些幾百磅重的動物
Few animals larger than a hundred pounds
從白堊紀晚期的大災難中倖存下來
survived the catastrophes of the late Cretaceous.
塵埃雲帶來長達數月的寒冷黑夜
The dust cloud brought night and cold to the surface for months.
恐龍因飢寒交迫而死
The dinosaurs froze and starved to death.
但還有一些在地下躲避的小動物
But there were small creatures who took shelter in the Earth.
等它們再次出現時
And when they emerged...
它們發現以前的獵食它們 威脅它們的惡霸都不見了
they found that the monsters who had hunted and terrorized them were gone.
地球變成了哺乳動物的天下
The Earth was becoming the Planet of the Mammals.
地球繼續不斷變化著
And the Earth continued its ceaseless changing.
這裏曾是寸草不生的荒漠
This was once a desert where nothing could grow.
只有1百萬平方英里的沙和鹽
It was a million square miles of sand and salt,
比現在地球上任何環境都要惡劣
far more hostile than any environment on Earth today.
白天溫度高的可以烤麵包
Daytime temperatures were hot enough to bake bread.
因為它處在海面之下1英里
And it was more than a mile below sea level,
因此大氣壓比現在高出50%
so the atmospheric pressure was about 50% higher than what we're used to.
很難想出還有什麼環境比這更令人絕望
It would be hard to think of a more unpromising environment on this planet.
在5百50萬年前 在變成海之前
Yet this was the basin of the Mediterranean five and a half million years ago,
這裏曾是地中海盆地
before it became a sea.
地球平靜的時間總是短暫的
The Earth never stops moving for long.
大盆地西端的天然大水壩
The natural dam at the western end of the deep basin
倒塌了 可能是因為地震
gave way, probably due to earthquakes.
洪災來了
And the deluge began.
兇猛的洪水規模甚至超過了尼加拉瓜大瀑布4萬倍
The torrential waters rushed in at a rate 40,000 times greater than Niagara Falls,
在不到一年的時間裏就將這遼闊的荒漠變成了地中海
turning a vast desert into the Mediterranean Sea... in less than a year
那時候人類還沒有出現
There were as yet no humans
無法目睹著壯麗的大洪水
to witness this enormous flood,
也無法感嘆它創造的美景
nor to admire the beauty it created.
與此同時 地球的另一端
Meanwhile, half a world away,
分開南北美洲的寬闊海峽
a broad channel separated North and South America...
使洋流可以從大西洋流入太平洋
allowing ocean currents to flow from the Atlantic into the Pacific Ocean.
最終因構造作用力逐漸將兩塊大陸集合在一起
Tectonic forces gradually brought these two continents together
閉合了海峽並創造了巴拿馬地峽
closing the channel and creating the Isthmus of Panama.
這重塑了全球洋流模式
This reorganized the worldwide pattern of ocean currents,
從而改變了全球的氣候
which, in turn, affected the global climate.
茂盛綠色森林覆蓋的非洲
In Africa, the lush green forest canopy
蛻變成了一片荒蕪
gave way to a sparser landscape.
一些專門生活在樹上的物種滅絕了
Some species that were highly specialized for life in the trees became extinct
但一些多面手們卻可以
But the generalists, the ones that could find a way
找到一條生存之道
to make a living no matter what life threw at them,
那就是 忍耐 然後進化
endured and evolved.
我們的遠古祖先曾經為了躲避地面的掠食者而藏身於地底深處
Our ancestors had once burrowed deep in the ground to avoid predators who stalked the surface.
當恐龍滅亡後
But when the dinosaurs perished,
它們重獲天日
they emerged into the daylight,
無數年後
and over the eons, made new lives
又爬回樹上
in the branches of the trees.
它們發育出適合抓握的拇指和腳趾
They developed opposable thumbs and toes
可以在樹枝間搖蕩 穿過寬闊的樹冠
for swinging from branch to branch, across the broad canopy of treetops,
從而滿足它們所有的需求
where all their needs were fulfilled.
它們也可以短暫的直立行走
They could also walk upright, but only for short distances.
周圍樹這麼多 它們也不需要走很遠
With so many trees around, they didn't have to go very far.
直到後來 氣溫下降 樹變得稀疏
But then it got colder, and the trees thinned out,
遼闊的草原涌現出來 我們的祖先
broad grasslands sprang up, and our ancestors
被迫穿過草原尋找食物
were forced to traverse them in search of food.
在熱帶大草原上 這就需要一套完全不同的技巧了
You needed a totally different skill set to make it on the savanna.
以前 可以悠閒地坐在樹枝上
In the old days, you could sit perched on your tree branch
遠遠地就能看到大型貓科動物
and watch the big cats from a safe distance.
現在 優勢不復存在
Now you were playing on the same dangerous field.
倖存者都是一些
The survivors were those who evolved the ability
可以用後肢長距離行走 並且能在必要時奔跑的
to walk great distances on their hind legs and to run when necessary.
這改變了它們觀察世界的方式
This changed the way they looked at the world.
行走時不再必須要有手和胳膊的幫助
Hands and arms were no longer tied up with walking.
它們可以自由的收集食物 拾取樹枝和骨頭
They were free to gather food and pick up sticks and bones.
用來製造武器和工具
These could be used as weapons and tools.
想想看
Think of it...
一小塊土地上的地形變化
A change in the topography of a small piece of land
再加上地球另一端的洋流變化
half a world away reroutes ocean currents.
使得非洲變得更冷更乾燥
Africa grows colder and drier.
大多數的樹無法適應新的氣候
Most of the trees can't withstand the new climate.
生活在其中的靈長類
The primates who lived in them
必須要尋找新的家園 不知不覺中
have to seek other homes, and before you know it,
它們使用工具開始改造這個星球
they're using tools to remake the planet.
地球改變了人類的命運
The Earth has shaped the course of human destiny,
還有遙遠世界的看不見的引力
but so has the invisible pull of distant worlds.
行星們影響著我們的生活
The planets have influenced our lives
不是你想的那個意思
but not in the way you think.
金星的引力
The gravitational pull of Venus--
不強卻很近
small but close--
木星的引力雖遠卻很強
and that of Jupiter-- distant but massive--
將地球的軸心拉向一側 一會這邊一會那邊
tilted the Earth's axis this way and that...
並且細微地扭曲了它的軌道
and ever so slightly tweaked the shape of its orbit.
這也週期性地改變了陽光照射在北部冰冠的數量
This periodically altered the amount of sunlight falling on the edge of the northern ice cap.
有時使那裏的夏天更冷
Sometimes it made the summers there colder,
並使冰川向南移動
and the glaciers advanced southward
年復一年
from one year to the next,
碾壓而過
grinding and scraping,
摧毀沿途的一切
and crushing everything in their path.
那就是我們說的冰河時期
That's what we call an ice age.
而另一時間 地球軸心和軌道的變化
At other times, changes in Earth's axis and orbit
使北極的夏天更熱
made the Arctic summers warmer.
並使冰川融化 向後退縮
And the melting glaciers began to retreat.
想像一下我們的祖先要有多大的本事
Imagine how resourceful our ancestors had to be
才能在這種氣候的巨變中倖存下來
in order to survive these radical changes in climate.
每個冰河時期
With each glacial period,
冰原都在侵蝕著海洋
the ice sheets grow at the expense of the oceans;
海平面下降超過400英尺
the world sea level falls by more than 400 feet,
約122米
沿著大陸的邊緣 使其露出大量的陸地
uncovering wide areas of land along the edges of the continents.
在1.5萬到2.5萬年前
15,000 to 25,000 years ago,
有過一次冰原後縮
there was a period when the ice receded,
暫時露出了一段連接的陸地
exposing a temporary land bridge.
通向地球另一半的大門緩緩開啟
The gateway to the other half of the planet swings open.
成群結隊的流浪者通過連接的陸地
Bands of wanderers crossed the land bridge
來到北美洲 有些去了南美洲
to North America and parts south.
大約1萬年前
About 10,000 years ago
氣候和海平面的反覆變化停止了
the manic swings of the climate and sea levels came to a stop.
一場新的更溫和的氣候時期到來了
A new and gentler climate age began.
就是我們現在生活的時期
It's the one we live in now.
當巨大的冰原融化時
When the great ice sheets melted,
海水升到現在的高度
the sea rose to its present height
河水攜帶高地而來的泥沙
and the rivers carried silt from the highlands
在流入大海時形成了河口沖積平原
to build great delta plains where they met the sea.
在那些富饒的平原上 我們學會了全新的生活方式
On those fertile plains, we learned a new way of life...
如何種植食物以解決飢餓
how to grow things, to feed ourselves and more.
對大部分人來說 這意味著一百萬年的遊蕩結束了
For most of us, this meant an end to a million years of wandering.
行星間的相互吸引
The way the planets tug at each other,
地球表面的移動
the way the skin of the Earth moves,
這些運動對於氣候的影響
the way those motions affect climate
對於生命和智力進化的影響
and the evolution of life and intelligence
它們集合在一起 使我們可以將
they all combined to give us the means
河口沖積平原的淤泥
to turn the mud of those river deltas
轉變為最初的文明
into the first civilizations.
間冰期是獨一無二的
There's nothing like an interglacial period,
冰河時期中的一段溫暖舒適的間歇
one of those balmy intermissions in an ice age.
好消息是這個時期 還將會持續
And the great news is that this one is due to last
5萬年
for another 50,000 years.
我們可以鬆口氣了
What a break for our kind.
還有一個問題
Just one problem.
我們貌似不停的消耗這些
We can't seem to stop burning up all those
從石炭紀就深埋地下的樹木
buried trees from way back in the Carboniferous Age,
它們已經是煤炭了
in the form of coal;
還有古代浮游生物的遺骸
and the remains of ancient plankton,
現在是石油和天然氣了
in the form of oil and gas.
如果可以停止 氣候上來說 我們就脫離危險了
If we could, we'd be home free, climate-wise.
然而 我們向空氣中排放二氧化碳的速度
Instead, we're dumping carbon dioxide into the atmosphere
是自過去那場導致大滅絕的災難以來
at a rate the Earth hasn't seen since the great climate catastrophes of the past,
前所未有的快
the ones that led to mass extinctions.
我們好像無法戒除我們對這些燃料的迷戀
We just can't seem to break our addiction to the kinds of fuel
沒有意識到這將會把我們帶回恐龍時代的氣候
that'll bring back a climate last seen by the dinosaurs;
在那種氣候下 我們的沿海城市會被淹沒
a climate that will drown our coastal cities and wreak havoc
同時也會嚴重破壞我們的壞境和影響我們的食物
on the environment and our ability to feed ourselves.
一直以來 壯麗的太陽
All the while, the glorious sun
灑下潔淨 免費的能量
pours immaculate, free energy down upon us;
遠遠超過我們的需要
more than we will ever need.
我們為什麼不能學習
Why can't we summon the ingenuity and courage
古人的智慧和勇氣呢
of the generations that came before us?
既然恐龍們沒有預見到小行星的來臨
The dinosaurs never saw that asteroid coming.
為什麼我們還不會引前車之鑒呢
What's our excuse?
有一條走廊
There's a corridor
就在滅絕紀念堂內
in the Halls of Extinction that is, right now,
依然空空蕩蕩
empty and unmarked.
地球的自傳依舊繼續書寫
The autobiography of the Earth is still being written.
有可能我們的故事就在此終結
There's a chance that the end of our story lies in there.
恭喜你
Congratulations.
你還活著
You're alive.
一條不間斷的線
There's an unbroken thread that stretches across
綿延跨越30億年
more than three billion years
將我們與這個世界上
that connects us to the first life
第一個生命聯繫起來
that ever touched this world.
想想我們無數的遠古祖先有多麼的
Think of how tough, resourceful and lucky
堅強 聰明 和幸運
all of our countless ancestors must have been
生存至今
to survive long enough
將生命的信息
to pass on the message of life to the next
一代又一代
and the next...
繼續接著一代又一代
and the next generation,
一直代代相傳
hundreds of millions of times...
傳到我們這一代
before it came to us.
需要跨過多少河流
There were so many rivers to cross,
期間還有無數的障礙
so many hazards along the way.
獵食者 饑荒 疾病
Predators, starvation, disease,
對形勢的誤判 漫長的寒冬
miscalculation, long winters,
旱災 洪災 暴力
drought, flood and violence.
還有偶爾從地下噴發的火山
Not to mention the occasional upheavals that erupted from within our planet
和天上落下的末日天體
and the apocalyptic bolts that come from the blue.
無論從我們起源何處
No matter where we hail from
我們的祖先是誰
or who our parents were, we are descended
我們都是不可思議的大災難的倖存者
from the hearty survivors of unimaginable catastrophes.
每個人都是在最漫長最危險的接力賽中的參賽者
Each of us is a runner in the longest and most dangerous relay race there ever was,
此時此刻 接力棒就在我們的手中
and at this moment, we hold the baton in our hands.
過去是截然不同的世界
The past is another planet.
未來將是如此
And so is the future.
大約2.5億年後
Some 250 million years from now,
許多地質學家認為地球上的陸地
many geologists think that the lands of the Earth
會再次聚合在一起
will be united once again.
這些美景將不復存在
All this beauty will have vanished
我們此時的地球
and the Earth of our moment in time
就變成了那時的失落世界
will take its place among the lost worlds.
板塊構造的偉大內部動力
The great internal engine of plate tectonics
對生命漠不關心
is indifferent to life,
就如同地球軌道和軸心的細微變化
as are the small changes in the Earth's orbit and tilt
還有偶爾來自小天體的撞擊
and the occasional collisions with little worlds on rogue orbits.
這些活動對於我們星球表面幾十億年裏
These processes have no notion of what has been going on
發生的事情完全沒有概念
over billions of years on our planet's surface.
它們不在乎
They do not care.
每個人都只是這顆小行星
Each of us is a tiny being
外殼上的乘客
riding on the outermost skin of one of the smaller planets
繞著自己的恆星走上幾十圈
for a few dozen trips around the local star.
地球上最古老的生物
The things that live the longest on Earth
也只不過堅持了地球年齡的百萬分之一
endure for only about a millionth of the age of our planet.
當然 任何一個有機體
So, of course, the individual organisms
是不可能看到
see nothing of the overall pattern.
大陸變化的全貌
Of changing continents...
氣候變化的全貌
climate...
進化的全貌
evolution.
我們明白 我們的小小起源
That we understand even a little of our origins
都是人類洞察和勇氣的偉大勝利之一
is one of the great triumphs of human insight and courage.
我們是誰 我們怎麼來到這裏
Who we are and why we are here can only be glimpsed
答案只能通過拼湊零星的碎片獲得
by piecing together something of the full picture,
完整的答案必然包含無數的時間
which must encompass eons of time...
幾百萬種物種
millions of species...
還有一大批的不同天體
and a multitude of worlds.
以這個角度看也不用感到奇怪
In this perspective, it's not surprising
那是因為我們本身就是一個謎
that we're a mystery to ourselves and that,
儘管我們很自豪
despite our manifest pretension,
但我們還不是這個小星球上的主人
we are far from being masters of our own little house.
這條走廊入口還沒有代表它的紀元的名稱
This new corridor has no name above the entrance to designate its epoch, and we don't yet know
也還不知道哪個滅亡的物種會被掛在牆上作為紀念
which failed species will be memorialized within its walls.
現在發生的一切 有無數的可能 可大可小
What happens here, in countless ways, both large and small,
而這一切都取決於我們
is being written by us.
現在的我們
Right now.
中文翻譯：@SaltyEggPain timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息